So
um obviously all of us are very used to
thinking about the fact that we have to
think about data analysis um at the same
time that we're thinking through
experimental design. This is equally so
obviously in the context of
computational modeling. it becomes it's
not impossible to take an experiment
that was designed not for computational
modeling maybe for statistical analyses
and develop a computational model for it
but a lot of the experimental
considerations that get optimized for
statistical analyses don't necessarily
translate perfectly to modeling um and
so I just wanted to bring this up
um so one of the
things that really is is very different
is that in statistical analyses often
what you're looking at
are values are values higher or lower in
some statistically significant way um
and in the context of computational
modeling what you're going to be doing
is creating an OD system so this is a
dynamical system that's going to have to
evolve over time in order for you to
create this system um you're going to
want to be able to test that the model
is actually accurate. And so you want to
think about it as okay, what ideally is
my model producing and is my experiment
set up to actually test that this model
is correct. Um so if you go back to this
glucose insulin model that we started
with, you'll notice that if you just
simply think about values, um many of
these different
um disorders look potentially
functionally identical, especially if
you consider just a single time point.
So if you're looking really just here,
um these two are going to look very
similar. And it's only when you consider
the dynamics that these disorders start
to look different. So the first thing to
mention is that even though it's very
common to take a single measurement in
the context of developing a
computational neuroscience model, what
you're going to want are to are to um
collect continuous
measures ideally over multiple
components of the circuit. So at the
bare minimum, if you have something that
involves let's say a negative feedback
loop, you would definitely need to
collect a signal at both the excitatory
and also the inhibitory components of
that negative feedback loop. So I know
this is challenging for people for
example who are doing electrophysiology
and for whom you know inserting an
electrode is a very big deal. Um but
picking those areas strategically
becomes very
important. Even better if you can
measure you know at more than two places
and actually as many places as possible
the better the coverage you have over
every one of these components
um the the better you're going to be
able to resolve the dynamics and also um
causality. The second point is well okay
so in in line with this you see that
just measuring one value here is
actually not going to be enough to
discriminate between these disorders. So
you want again to measure across
different components. um you want the
dynamics um and also you need to
consider that because you're going to be
focusing very deeply on the dynamics
um averaging time series can be
potentially a problem because you're
going to wash out your dynamics to some
degree and so for that reason if
possible you want to maximize your SNR
your signal to noise ratio over long
data rather than low SNR over short
data. Um and that actually goes against
some of the principles that are used in
some of these in neuro imaging these
huge data sets like UK bioank where you
have you know um very short resting
state data but over huge amounts of you
know huge numbers of people and the
assumption is that having lots of people
sort of makes makes up for the fact that
the data quality um is for each
individual is not as good.
The other thing you might want to
consider is that one of the advantages
of computational modeling is you can
design what I call in a critical
experiment. What you want to be able to
do is to set up your model to consider
potentially competing hypotheses. So
very often in
neuroscience there are many competing
ideas about how the circuit is set up um
what their functions are. And the beauty
of modeling is that you can model each
one of those competing hypotheses and
ask what their outputs would look like
dynamically and then see where those
outputs maximally diverge and then
design the experiment to measure exactly
where they maximally diverge so that you
can discriminate between those competing
hypotheses. This is a very powerful way
to use models. So again, not even if you
say, okay, I I don't have enough
information about the system to be sure
about how this model is set up, even
being able to set up a provisional
circuit with lots of different ways of
doing it. In principle, you could look
at all the combinatorial ways that the
circuit could be set up and ask what
those outputs would be and then let the
data tell you which of
those configurations are compatible with
the data and which ones are not.
Um and then the other advantage of the
model in that from that perspective is
that you can perturb the circuit in
silicone. You can ask what would happen
if I would were to stimulate the circuit
here versus here versus here. How would
it affect the dynamics? So again you can
do these incilico experiments that then
can create testable hypotheses which can
then be tested.
Um, my last point is that if you're
going to take advantage of the of the
multis-cale capabilities of neuroblocks,
you want to make sure that you validate
these by also collecting data across
multiple scales and ideally
simultaneously so that you then you can
develop the transfer functions that
allow you to ask how do you get from the
bottom layer to the next layer to the
next layer to the next layer.
Um, so again, I'm not saying that these
are easy experiments to conduct, but
it's something to consider if your
ultimate aim is to
um to create a a rigorous model.